so here's the question for you what is
the maximum speed at which a car
can safely round a turn of radius 90
meters
if the coefficient of static friction is
0.75
so let's say a car
is making a circular turn
i'm going to draw a box to represent the
car
so it's going in that direction
how can we calculate
the coefficient of static friction
that allows it to make the turn
now we need to understand is that static
friction
is directed this way
whenever car makes a circular turn
static friction between the road and the
tires
allows it to make the turn so static
friction provides the centripetal force
so the net force
in
the x direction for this problem
is equal to the static frictional force
that's the only other force acting in
that direction
and we know that the net force is mass
times acceleration
so it's just m a
and the static frictional force is mu s
times the normal force
now the acceleration in the x direction
or towards the center of the circle is
the centripetal acceleration
which is v squared divided by r
the normal force
on a horizontal flat surface
is seen simply equal to the weight of
the object
which is mg
so in this problem we can cancel the
mass
the maximum speed of the car does not
depend on the mass
so what we have left over is v squared
divided by r
which is equal to mu s
times g
so let's multiply both sides by r
so what we have now is v squared is
equal to mu s
times g times r
and now let's take the square root of
both sides
so the maximum speed
that the car can safely make the turn
is equal to the square root
of mu s times rg
so that's
0.75
times the radius which is 90
times the gravitational acceleration of
9.8 meters per second squared
so the answer is about 25.7
per second
and so that's how you could find the
maximum speed
that a vehicle can safely make a certain
turn
given the coefficient of static friction
here's another one
number two
calculate the coefficient of static
friction
if a car can round a turn of radius 70
meters
at a speed of 24 meters per second
so based on the last problem go ahead
and try this one
so just like before
we know that
the net force
okay i'm not sure what just happened
let's do that again
the net force is equal to the static
frictional force
and this is going to be m a
that's equal to mu s times the normal
force
and a is the centripetal acceleration
so that's a v squared
over r
and the normal force is just
mg
now this time we're looking for mu s
so i'm going to multiply both sides by
1 over g
it's on the right g is going to cancel
so v squared divided by rg
is equal to the coefficient of static
friction
so this is the formula that we need
in this problem
so mu s is going to be
24 squared
divided by the radius of 70
times
9.8
24 squared
is 576.
70 times 9.8
is 686
so dividing these two numbers
you should get .84
if you rounded to nearest hundredth
place
and so that's the coefficient of static
friction
that will allow the car
to make a turn of radius 70 meters
at this speed
and so that's it for this
problem so here's another problem that
we could try
a rotor ride has a radius of 8 meters
and rotates at a speed of 25 rpms
what is the minimum coefficient of
static friction
that will prevent people from slipping
down when the floor drops up
so let's draw a picture
and a typical roto ride looks like a
cylinder
and let's draw a person
now as the ride spins
and as the floor drops out
the person if he's moving fast enough
will not fall down
now how does that work
well the person wants to fly out this
way
but instead
based on the curvature of the room as it
rotates it forces him to turn in a
circle
so therefore the wall
exerts a normal force on a person
the person feels like he's being pressed
against the wall
but his inertia wants him to keep going
forward but based on the curvature of
the wall as it spins it forces him to
turn into a circle so the wall exerts a
normal force in this direction
the person's weight force wants to bring
him down
and static friction prevents him from
sliding down
now as you increase the speed the normal
force increases
which in turn increases the static
frictional force
which supports the weight of the person
so there's a minimum speed at which
this rotor ride has to spin at in order
to support the weight of the person
our goal is to find the minimum
coefficient of static friction
so we need just enough frictional force
to support the weight so we're going to
set those two equal to each other
so ffs is equal to mg
now static friction is equal to mu s
times the normal force
so how can we calculate the normal force
notice that the normal force
points towards
the center of the circle
so therefore the normal force provides
the centripetal force it keeps the
person moving
in circular motion
so we can say that the normal force is
equal to the centripetal force
and therefore the normal force is mv
squared over r
so now we have mu s
times mv squared over r
is equal to mg
so now we could cancel m
so mu s is independent of the mass so we
have mu s v squared over r
equals g
now to get mu s by itself let's multiply
both sides by r
over v squared
on the left side we can cancel v squared
and we can cancel r
so mu s in this problem
is equal
to rg
over v squared
now
we have r we know what g is
the only thing we're missing is the
speed in meters per second we have it
in rpms that is revolutions per minute
so let's just get rid of some stuff
first
and i'm just going to rewrite this
equation on top so i have more working
space
so how can we convert rpms into meters
per second
i'm going to do it two ways
the first
is to find a frequency in a period
so what we have is 25 revolutions
per minute
so that means that
there's 25 revolutions
for every 60 seconds
because one minute equals 60 seconds
now if you want to find a frequency it's
basically equal to number of cycles
divided by the time
so there's 25 cycles or 25 revolutions
that occur in a time of 60 seconds
so this is equal to 0.4167
revolutions per second or cycles per
second
now the period
is 1 over f 1 over the frequency
so it's 1 over 0.4167
or 60 over 25
so you should get 2.4 seconds for the
period
now the speed
is 2 pi r
divided by the period
it's distance over time and the distance
around a circle
is the circumference of a circle
so if you want to derive this equation
you can start
from this equation
so we know that d is equal to vt when an
object is moving with constant speed
so v
is d divided by t
the distance of a circle as we said
before is the circumference of a circle
which is 2 pi r
and the time it takes to travel around
the circle is known as a period
so v is equal to 2 pi r over t
so that's how you can get that equation
if you're wondering
so now once we have it we can now find a
speed so it's 2 pi times a radius of 8
meters
divided by a period of 2.4 seconds
so that's going to be 20.94
meters per second
which i'm going to write
at the top
so now what's another way in which we
can convert rpms directly
into meters per second
so if you want to use a conversion
process
here's what you could do
so this is how you convert linear speed
or rather angular speed into linear
speed this is linear speed
angle speed is like rpms
revolutions per second radians per
minute and things like that
angular speed tells you how fast you're
spinning linear speed tells you how fast
moving forward
so we're going to start with 25
revolutions per minute
and one minute
is equal to 60 seconds because we need
to get meters per second
so the unit minutes cancel
now
one revolution around a circle
is equal to two pi radians which is 360
degrees
now the radius of the circle is eight
meters
so that means that
one radian
has a length of eight meters
so now the units revolutions cancel
and the units
radians cancel
so now what we have left over
is meters
per second
so let's get the answer it's 25 divided
by 60
times 2 pi times 8
and that will give you the same answer
of 20.94
now that we have the speed
let's calculate the coefficient of
static friction
so let's get the final answer
so mu s is equal to the radius of 8
meters
times the gravitational acceleration
of 9.8 meters per second squared
divided by the speed
which is
20.94 meters per second i'm going to
square that as well
so i got
.179
for the coefficient of static friction
so that's the minimum amount that we
need
so when that the floor drops out
the people won't slide down they're
going to stay where they are static
friction is going to support the weight
you